Samuel Wylie Crawford Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Samuel Wylie Crawford Papers 1860-1892
MSS17194
Crawford, Samuel Wylie, 1827-1892
400 items
7 containers plus 1 oversize
1.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Physician and army officer. Diary, correspondence, memoranda, registers and returns of troops and artillery, sketches, photographs, and other items relating chiefly to events while Crawford was an assistant surgeon at Fort Sumter during the early months of 1861.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Anderson, Robert, 1805-1871--Correspondence.; Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893--Correspondence.; Capers, Ellison, 1837-1908--Correspondence.; Crawford, Samuel Wylie, 1827-1892.; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889--Correspondence.; Gregg, Maxcy, 1814-1862--Correspondence.; Lee, Robert E. (Robert Edward), 1807-1870--Correspondence.; Magrath, A. G. (Andrew Gordon), 1813-1893--Correspondence.; Memminger, C. G. (Christopher Gustavus), 1803-1888--Correspondence.; Pemberton, John C. (John Clifford), 1814-1881--Correspondence.; Pickens, F. W. (Francis Wilkinson), 1805-1869--Correspondence.; Porter, David D. (David Dixon), 1813-1891.; Ripley, R. S. (Roswell Sabine), 1823-1887--Correspondence.
Organizations
Powhatan (Side-wheel steamer); United States. Army--Supplies and stores.
Subjects
Military supplies.
Places
Charleston (S.C.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Fort Sumter (Charleston, S.C.)--Siege, 1861.; South Carolina--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Medical care.
Occupations
Army officers.; Physicians.
Provenance
The papers of Samuel Wylie Crawford, physician and army officer, were given to the Library of Congress by Eva Anderson Lawton, 1916-1918. An addition was given by Luther M. Cornwall in 1939, and other material was purchased in 1915.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Samuel Wylie Crawford are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Samuel Wylie Crawford (1827-1892), span the years 1860-1892. The papers consists of diaries, letters received and copies of letters sent, memoranda, registers and returns of troops and artillery, sketches, photographs, and other items relating chiefly to events while Crawford was an assistant surgeon at Fort Sumter.
The papers contain correspondence from Governor Francis W. Pickens of South Carolina, including letters to Jefferson Davis; copies of correspondence between Robert Anderson and G.T. Beauregard before the bombardment of Fort Sumter; and a statement by David D. Porter concerning the frigate Powhatan and the provisioning of Fort Sumter. Correspondents include Ellison Capers, Maxcy Gregg, Robert E. Lee, A. G. Magrath, C. G. Memminger, John C. Pemberton, and Roswell Sabine Ripley.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Chronological file (Box 1)
  - 1860, Apr. 17-1861, Feb 4; May 1 (Box 1)
  - 1861, Feb. 5-1863, July 1 (Box 2)
  - 1863, July 10-1873, Mar. 25 (Box 3)
  - 1873, Mar. 25-1892, Oct. 13 (Box 4)
- Diary, Fort Sumter, S.C., 1860, Dec.19-1861, Apr. 1 (Box 5)
- Letterbook, 1861, Jan. 23-1862, May 18 (Box 6)
- Miscellany, 1860-1861 See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 7)
- Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Miscellany, 1860-1861 (Box OV 1)